# Thaylo Xavier de Freitas

# Summary

Technology professional with 10+ years in software engineering and system design for industrial and consumer-facing systems. Working in management roles in the Oil & Energy industry since 2023, navigating agile startup environments and structured corporate settings.

# Work Experience

Mar 2024–Present LLM Engineer | Founder, WeOptimize Tecnologia LTDA - Part-time 10 hours per

Product discovery, research, and software engineering for LLM applications using cloud and self-hosted LLMs.

For Whatsapp bot implementation, integrated LangChain agents with Twilio and MCPs. LLM running on self-hosted Deepseek-R1:14b for cost reduction during the proof-of-concept phase. Created and organized work instructions, processes, and policies for WeOptimize to enable fast onboarding and business agility.

Technology stacks: AWS, Linux, Langchain, Ollama, Docker, MCP, ReAct, Chain-of-thought

Tooling in Use: AWS codecommit, ngrok, OpenAI API Platform, Anthropic API Platform, codex cli, claude code, and claude desktop.

Apr 2024–Present Automation Engineer | Local IT Coordinator, BK Consulting - Full-time employment.

> Started working as an individual contributor in a local IT team of 5 developers, delivering solutions made with Power BI, Python, and SAP Scripting. In November 2024, began coordinating the local IT team.

> I worked for Petrobras SA's Mooring Systems department through Capco for 2 months before transitioning to this contract on behalf of BK Consulting when they secured this long-term contract.

> Proof of concepts, SAP Scripting and TDV-enabled SAP data extraction using Python to organize material management data (material movements, material certificates, service orders,

Jun 2022–Aug 2023

# **Software Dev. Coordinator** | **Technology Manager**, Deep Seed Solutions.

Started as SW development coordinator before promotion to Technology Manager after 7 months for defining and documenting SW and IT procedures. Led a team of 8 developers; implemented code review and unit testing. Conducted financial evaluations for hardware purchases. Designed technical scope for ArcGIS 3D integration with FLOCO, having the software implementation delivered on time.

Stack: Linux, AWS, Docker, Git, Qt, C++, Python, Postgres, and SQLite.

Jul 2021–Jun 2022

### **Software Development Engineer II**, Amazon.

Implemented features on global tax calculation services using Java and Amazon's proprietary deployment pipelines. Undertook "on-call" rotations supporting Brazilian tax calculation workloads, monitoring and responding to service alarms.

#### Jul 2019–Jul 2021 **Project Analyst II**, Tata Consultancy Services.

As Solution Architect for IoT/OT, supported VALE's Safety Transformation Program by implementing ISO CxS, TPMS, and Fleet Management technologies in earth-moving equipment fleets at S11D, Carajás, Serra Leste, and Onça Puma. Contributed to Global Geotech Program's automated dam monitoring systems.

Stack: Docker, Git, and Python.

Aug 2017–Nov 2018 Software Developer, ESSS, Vixteam, Conexos.

Had multiple short-term experiences in web development across three companies. Acquired skills in Docker containerization, Java Spring Boot frameworks, and system architecture design principles.

Nov 2015–Dec 2016 Control Systems Software Engineer, LYNX Process.

Implemented collision avoidance logic (C#, SQL) for large-scale industrial machinery at iron ore stockyards using non-linear optimization with GPS RTK data. Developed an algorithm generating 50% CAPEX savings by eliminating 10 lidar sensors (valued around 50k BRL each).

Sep 2014–Jun 2015 **Software Engineer I**, Muxi Tecnologia em Pagamentos S.A..

Developed a WMS Browser for POS machines in C89. Created a custom hash table implementation that reduced device boot time from ten minutes to under twenty seconds.

## Education

2024 Executive MBA in Project Management, Fundação Getúlio Vargas.

2015 **Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Engineering**, Federal University of Espírito Santo.

## **Technical Skills**

Core Skills Agile and traditional project management, cloud and back-end software engineering

Programming Python, C, Java, C#, JavaScript, C++

Libraries Django, FastAPI, Spring Boot, OpenGL, Pydantic, Qt, Langchain

Data Technologies SAP Scripting, Power BI, SQL, MongoDB, PostgreSQL

Infrastructure Docker, AWS, Git, CI/CD pipelines

# Awards & Publications

Courses UDEMY: (8.5 hours) LangChain - Develop LLM powered applications with

LangChain - Aug. 31, 2024

Competitions International Robotics: 1st place, UFES' TRUFES (2013); 2nd place, LARC Open (2013);

3rd place, LARC IEEE VSSS (2014).

Publications Robotic Soccer Team Using a Multilayered Control Architecture, LARC, 2015; Multi-

Layered Control Applied to Autonomous Robot Soccer, LARC, 2014; Introdução à

Programação: Uma Nova Abordagem Usando C, Elsevier, 2014 (co-author)

## Activities

Teaching Teaching assistant for C, Python, and Haskell programming languages in Data Processing I, II, and Data Structures courses for Computer Engineering and Computer

Science programs at UFES.